Finding Aid for Twichell Family Papers, 1831-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Twichell Family papers 1831-1975, 1844-1975
Twichell family.
1 oversize folders
3.5 linear feet
85470 Aa 2; UAl
Hamburg, Livingston County, and Ann Arbor, Michigan, family. Correspondence, newspaper clippings and photographs of the Lohmiller, Twichell, and Hollister families.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Jean L. Rich (donor no. 5775 ) and from her estate in several accessions, 1975-1997.
The collection is open to research.
This collection focuses on the lives and families of three Michigan women, Marietta "Etta" Hollister Rorabacher Twichell, Jennie May Twichell Lohmiller, and Jean Lohmiller Rich. The Hollister family in Michigan was begun by Rev. and Mrs. Algernon Hollister, who emigrated to Michigan from New York in 1837, settling eventually in Hamburg, Michigan, part of Livingston County. Their granddaughter, Etta Hollister, was born in 1852. In 1881, she wed her second husband, Hobart A. Twichell. Hobart was born in Connecticut in 1800, and moved to Livingston County, Michigan at the age of twenty-five, where he farmed for most of his life. Born in 1881, their daughter Jennie May Twichell married William Lohmiller in 1919. The Lohmiller family emigrated from Germany and settled in and around Sparta and LaCrosse, Wisconsin. William Lohmiller moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan, where he and his wife owned and operated a boarding house during the 1920s and 1930s (as had other members of the Twichell family). Mrs. Lohmiller also taught in the Menominee and Hamburg school systems. Their only daughter, Jean Lohmiller Rich, taught in Lincoln Park, Michigan, while her husband Ed Rich worked for Allied Chemical Company in Detroit. Members of the Hollister, Twichell and Lohmiller families married into the Hickox, Culver, DePue, McClure, Rorabacher, Scott, and Wilner families, among many others.
The papers of the Twichell family document three generations of the extended Twichell families. It includes extensive correspondence files, reminiscences of life on turn-of-the-century Michigan farm and of student life the University of Michigan, files relating to the family businesses including boardinghouses in Ann Arbor, and photographs of family members, towns in Michigan, and University of Michigan students. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence, Alphabetical Files, Photographs, and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Depew family.; Farm life--Michigan.; Farms--Michigan--Hamburg.; Hamburg (Mich.); Hollister family.; Livingston County (Mich.); Lohmiller family.; Menominee (Mich.); Teachers--Michigan--Hamburg.; Teachers--Michigan--Menominee.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1941-1950.; Women teachers--Michigan--Hamburg.; Women teachers--Michigan--Menominee.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Aged persons.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Arizona.; Automobiles.; Bicycles and tricycles.; Boy Scouts of America.; Brighton (Mich.); Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Manistee.; Butler family.; California.; Carriages and coaches.; Carts and wagons.; Cats.; Children.; Church Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Classrooms--Michigan--Hamburg.; Clothing and dress.; Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Families.; Ferries.; Floods.; Florida.; Frankfort (Mich.); Hamburg (Mich.); Hamburg (Mich.)--Schools.; Hayes family.; Hollister family.; Hunting--United States.; Interiors.; Lakeland (Mich.); Lohmiller family.; Louis Sands Salt and Lumber Company (Manistee, Mich.); Lumber industry.; Manistee (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Manistee River (Mich.); Menominee (Mich.); Nursing.; Packard Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Phi Delta Phi. Kent Chapter (University of Michigan); Railroads--Michigan.; Remer (Minn.); Rorabacher family.; Schlede Bookstore (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Schlede family.; Schlede House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Hamburg.; Scott family.; Sheboygan (Wis.); Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Tourism.; Twichell family.; University of Michigan--Students.; Wisconsin.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Cyanotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence 1831-1971
  The Correspondence Series consists of letters from the Hollister and Twichell families dating from 1831 to 1959. Most of this correspondence was sent or received by Etta Twichell and her daughter Jennie. There are a few Civil War period letters, but most of these don't mention the conflict. Of particular interest are the letters to Etta Twichell from M.S. Hollister as he migrated west through Arizona and California, and from Joseph Hollister, who settled in Idaho. There are also letters by Jennie Twichell Lohmiller describing her work as a teacher. The series also contains letters from friends and relatives describing preparations for World War I. The series also includes letters of Jean Lohmiller Rich, 1930-1971, with her family and with her husband Ed Rich. These letters relate to their careers and their personal relationship.
  - 1831, 1844-1859 (Box 1)
  - 1860-1869 (Box 1)
  - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
  - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900-1909, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1910-1919, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - 1920-1929, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1930-1939, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Jean Lohmiller Rich 1930-1971 (Box 1)
  - Jean Lohmiller Rich and Ed Rich 1947-1952, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Alphabetical Files 1859-1975
  The Alphabetical Files contain clippings, documents and ephemeral materials saved by various members of this family. In some cases, these materials have been arranged into folders corresponding to the individual who created it, or the family who is its subject. In other cases, the files were created around a particular format or subject. In addition, notes and reminiscences written by Jennie Twichell Lohmiller summarize some of the information scattered in other folders. Her files also contain her reminiscence of life as a child on a turn-of-the-century Michigan farm. There is also material concerning University of Michigan life in the Martha Cook Dormitory, and the Triangle Engineering Fraternity, especially during the 1940s and 1950s. Account ledgers document the transactions of the Ann Arbor boarding houses run by the Twichell and Lohmiller families. There are two folders of newspaper clippings, most related to the Hollister and Twichell families, and many dating from the 19th century. Another file contains poetry manuscripts from the 1860s, dealing with Civil War themes. Although there is no author noted on most of them, one was written by "Alsena" of Hamburg, Michigan (probably Alcena Twichell DePue, 1843-1936, of Hamburg). The files on different families and individuals contain clippings, notes, anecdotes, documents, and ephemeral materials.
  - Ann Arbor Boarding House Records of Twichell and Lohmiller Families, ca. 1898, 1921-1942 (Box 2)
  - Barnard, Lois (Notebook) undated (Box 2)
  - Civil War Poems 1859-1865, undated (Box 2)
  - Deeds and Mortgages, ca. 1836-1920 (Box 2)
  - Diaries
    - Trip to Western United States 1912 (Box 2)
    - Jean Lohmiller Rich 1936-1943 (Box 2)
  - Hollister Family History 1885, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Hollister, Grace, Autograph Book, ca. 1882-1885 (Box 2)
  - Lohmiller Family undated (Box 2)
  - Lohmiller, Jennie Twichell
    - Account Book Undated (Box 2)
    - Family Documents and Mementos, ca. 1900-1974 (Box 2)
    - Notes on Her Life and Her Family undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Reminiscences of Childhood
      - Typescript undated (Box 2)
      - Audio Tapes 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - Midland, Michigan, Northeast Intermediate School 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings circa 1870-1950 (Box 2)
  - Notebooks, Unidentified (Box 2)
  - Rich, Jean Lohmiller (Genealogy Workbook) undated (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1920, undated (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    - Sermon by Rev. Algernon Sidney Hollister 1846 (Box 2)
    - Girls and Boys Clubs, ca. 1917 (Box 2)
    - Junior Red Cross Township Meeting 1919 (Box 2)
  - Twichell Family
    - Genealogy Notes undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Significant Documents (mostly Hobart Twichell's) 1844, 1878, 1897 undated (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - Martha Cook Dormitory (Jean Lohmiller Rich?) 1951 (Box 2)
    - Triangle Fraternity: Photographs and Newsletter, 1942-1951 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs Series is divided into three subseries and consists entirely of prints. Many of the photographs were obviously taken in the nineteenth century, but very few are precisely dated. However, many of the subjects in these photographs are identified. The first subseries contains portraits and candid photos of various individuals and families on the Twichell family tree. The "Places" subseries contains photos from several towns in Michigan. These appear to date from around the turn of the century, or the early decades of the twentieth century. The "Topical" subseries contains portraits of boarders who attended the University of Michigan. Also, there are some interesting, if poorly identified, photographs of lumbering in Michigan.
  - Families and Individuals
    - Butler Family (Box 3)
    - Family and Friends A-M (Box 3)
    - Family and Friends N-Z (Box 3)
    - Hayes Family (Box 3)
    - Hollister Family, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lohmiller Family, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Rich, Jean (Box 3)
    - Rich, Ed and Jean Lohmiller (Box 3)
    - Rorabacher Family (Box 3)
    - Schlede, Grace Hollister (Box 3)
    - Scott Family (Box 3)
    - Twichell, Etta, Western Tour (?) (Box 3)
    - Twichell Family, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Unidentified (Box 3)
      (include tintype in case)
  - Places
    - Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 3)
    - Hamburg, Michigan (Box 3)
    - Lakeland, Michigan (Box 3)
    - Menominee, Michigan (Box 3)
    - Remer, Minnesota (Box 3)
    - Sheboygan (Wis.) (Box 3)
  - Topical
    - Boarders connected with Twichell Boarding House and University of Michigan (Box 3)
    - Houses, Businesses (Box 3)
      (Includes photos of Schlede Bookstore, Ann Arbor)
    - Lumbering (Box 3)
      (Includes photos of Logging Railroads)
    - Men Who Worked at Twichell Boarding Houses at 1325 Geddes and 5215 East University 1899-1905 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      (see also UAl oversize folder for Girls Washington Club, Ann Arbor High Schools, April 14, 1941)
    - Phi Delta Phi (Box 3)
      (see oversize UAl)
    - University of Michigan Student Body 1913 (Box 3)
      (see oversize folder UAl)
    - Western Tour (?) (Box 3)
  - Albums
    - Portrait Album, 19th century (Box 3)
    - Unidentified (Box 3)
      (includes photographs from California and Arizona)
    - Hobart Twichell and Family (Box 4)
    - "Cena T. DePue's Book" (Box 4)
    - Unidentified Ann Arbor people/places, ca. 1945 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 19th century (Box 4)
    (include Lohmiller)
- Sound recordings
  - Ed Rich (?) reminiscences, 4 audiocassettes (Box 4)
  - Reminiscences of Triangle Fraternity by Ed Rich, ca. 1975, 1 audiocassettes (Box 4)